Finding Aid for Albert M. Barrett papers, 1900-1937
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Albert M. Barrett papers 1900-1937
Barrett, Albert M. (Albert Moore), 1871-1936.
9766 Aa 2
Physician, early specialist in the treatment of mental illness; correspondence; topical files; lectures and publications; casework; and photographs.
3 linear feet in 4 boxes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The Albert M. Barrett papers were donated as part of the Raymond Waggoner papers (donor 6921 ) in 1984.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open for research, except for the case files in box 4 which are restricted for 100 years from date of creation.
Albert Moore Barrett was hired by the University of Michigan in 1906 to organize the first university hospital and clinic in the United States specifically devoted to the treatment of mental diseases. Barrett was born in Austin, Illinois on July 15, 1871, and earned Bachelor of Arts and Medical degrees from the State University of Iowa in 1893 and 1895, respectively. He received postgraduate training in psychiatry at Heidelberg University, Germany, in 1901 and 1902.
Before working at the University of Michigan, Barrett was a pathologist at the Independence, Iowa State Hospital for the Insane from 1895 to 1897 and 1898 to 1901; assistant physician at the Worcester, Massachusetts State Hospital for the Insane, 1897-1898; pathologist at the Danvers, Massachusetts State Hospital for the Insane between 1902 and 1905; and assistant professor of neuropathology at Harvard University during the 1905-1906 academic year.
Barrett was part of a movement in the treatment of mentally ill people which viewed mental illnesses as potentially treatable problems, and which discouraged incarcerating the mentally ill in asylums or penal institutions if at all possible. His work as director of the State Psychopathic Hospital in Ann Arbor was path-breaking in several respects, particularly in the treatment of less severe cases on an outpatient or short-term basis. Barrett saw his model of a psychopathic hospital as a supplement to the existing system of state hospitals for the insane, and believed that a system of mental health centers affiliated with local hospitals would be more effective than the existing, highly centralized, arrangements in each state; it would allow for cooperation with local courts and welfare agencies, and would let patients remain close to home whenever possible.
One of Barrett's main goals was to create a training center for psychiatric workers; making sure that mental patients were treated by properly trained professionals was part of the general trend toward creating a more positive therapeutic environment for the mentally ill. The affiliation of the State Psychopathic Hospital with the University of Michigan was especially useful, because it allowed observation and research along with treatment of patients. Barrett's ideas and work provided the template for future psychiatric education programs at the University of Michigan. He died suddenly on April 2, 1936.
The Albert M. Barrett papers comprise 3 linear feet, and have been divided into five series: Correspondence; Topical Files; Lectures and Publications; Photographs; and Casework.
Subjects:
Barrett, Albert M. (Albert Moore), 1871-1936.; Psychiatry.; Psychiatric hospitals--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Kalamazoo State Hospital (Mich.); University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Medical School.; University of Michigan. Department of Psychiatry.; Mental health.; Leopold, Nathan Freudenthal, 1904-1971.; Loeb, Richard A., 1905-1936.; State Psychopathic Hospital at the University of Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Barrett, Albert M. (Albert Moore), 1871-1936.; Mental institutions--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; State Psychopathic Hospital at the University of Michigan.; Psychiatry--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series [1.1 linear ft.; 1905-1937] contains letters and memoranda, most of which relate to Barrett's duties as director of the Psychopathic Hospital. There is extensive correspondence with national mental health organizations, staff of state and federal agencies, and other medical practitioners. Topics covered include administration and staffing of the hospital and teaching programs, as well as Barrett's own research. The latter is interspersed through the "Miscellaneous Correspondence, chronological" files in box 1.
  - American Neurological Association 1933-1936 (Box 1)
  - American Psychiatric Association 1911-1936 (Box 1)
  - Angell, James B. 1907-1909 (Box 1)
  - Camp, Carl D. 1907 (Box 1)
  - Christian, E.A. 1913 (Box 1)
  - Cram, Esther M. 1931-1934 (Box 1)
  - Dana, Charles 1913 (Box 1)
  - de Nancrede, C.B.G. 1908 (Box 1)
  - Detroit Society of Neurology and Psychiatry 1908-1919 (Box 1)
  - Ferris, Governor Woodbridge N. 1913-1915 (Box 1)
  - Fitzgerald, Governor Frank D. 1934-1936 (Box 1)
  - Furstenburg, Dr. A.C. 1935 (Box 1)
  - G-H 1907-1935, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Institute for Psychoanalysis 1931-1936 (Box 1)
  - J 1913-1918 (Box 1)
  - Kline, George M. 1913-1933 (Box 1)
  - Masserman, Jules H. 1934 (Box 1)
  - Meyer, Adolf 1906-1934 (Box 1)
  - Michigan
    - Attorney General 1906-1918 (Box 1)
    - Board of Corrections and Charities 1912-1916 (Box 1)
    - Society for Mental Hygiene 1919-1936 (Box 1)
    - State Asylum for the Insane
      - General 1905-1920, 3 folders (Box 1)
      - Superintendents 1906-1907 (Box 1)
    - State Legislature 1932-1934 (Box 1)
    - State Medical Society 1912-1936 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, chronological order 1905-1936, 14 folders (Box 1)
  - National Association for the Study of Epilepsy 1909 (Box 1)
  - National Committee for Mental Hygiene 1907-1936 (Box 1)
  - National Committee on Dementia Praecox 1934-1935 (Box 1)
  - Postgraduate Psychiatry Seminar 1933-1934 (Box 1)
  - Ruthven, Alexander G. 1930-1934 (Box 1)
  - Secretary of State 1909 (Box 1)
  - Southard, E.E. 1909-1935 (Box 1)
  - State Psychopathic Hospital 1906-1919
    - Board of Trustees 1905-1920 (Box 1)
    - Building Project 1907-1915 (Box 1)
    - Interim Director 1936-1937 (Box 1)
  - Tennant, Agnes 1907 (Box 1)
  - University of Michigan Department of Nervous Diseases and Psychiatry 1910-1917 (Box 1)
  - War Department 1917-1927 (Box 2)
  - Wayne County Clinic for Child Study 1934-1935 (Box 2)
  - Williams, Frankwood E. 1912-1914 (Box 2)
  - Works Progress Administration 1935-1936 (Box 2)
- Topical Files
  Topical Files [.7 linear ft.; 1900-1936] consist of correspondence, memoranda and reports relating to a wide variety of issues which were of interest to Barrett. The "State Psychiatric Hospital [SPH]" and "University of Michigan" files are particularly interesting, because they contain information about training programs for psychiatric medical staff, as well as details about building plans for the hospital. "SPH: Statistics and General Information" contains statistical charts of patient information, which are broken down by ethnicity, sex and disease diagnosis. The "Guide for the Preparation of Histories..." and "SPH: Nursing" files provide a sense of interaction between mental hospital staff and patients. This series also contains a "Biographical Information" file about Barrett.
  - American Medical Association 1930-1936 (Box 2)
  - American Neurological Association 1933-1936 (Box 2)
  - Barnes, Florence B. (UM Department of Psychology) undated (Box 2)
  - Biographical Information undated (Box 2)
  - Christian, Edmund, eulogy 1935 (Box 2)
  - Feeblemindedness 1915 (Box 2)
  - Guide for the Preparation of Histories and for the Psychiatric Examination of Cases of Mental Disorders undated (Box 2)
  - Heidelberg Study 1900-1901 (Box 2)
  - Juvenile Delinquency 1934-1936 (Box 2)
  - Kalamazoo State Hospital Outpatient Care circa 1928 (Box 2)
  - MacGregor Fund 1935 (Box 2)
  - National Committee for Mental Hygiene, Division of Psychiatric Education 1930-1936, 6 folders (Box 2)
  - Psycho-neuroses undated (Box 2)
  - Rockefeller Foundation 1933-1936 (Box 2)
  - State Psychiatric Hospital (SPH)
    - Building Project 1931-1935, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Director's Report 1935 (Box 2)
    - Laboratory Statistics and Activities 1932-1936 (Box 2)
    - Nursing 1921 (Box 2)
    - Statistics and General Information 1920-1935, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Sterilization Bill 1911, undated (Box 2)
  - University of Michigan
    - Department of Psychiatry-Reports to Dean 1910, 1923, undated (Box 2)
    - General Hospital-Statistical Program 1933-1934 (Box 2)
    - Graduate School Correspondence 1935-1936 (Box 2)
    - Psychiatric Instruction circa 1925-1933 (Box 2)
  - Veterans Administration 1935-1936 (Box 2)
- Lectures and Publications
  The Lectures and Publications series [.7 linear ft.; 1905-c.1930s] contains addresses, lecture notes and reprints of articles by Barrett. Topics vary, from mental diseases and conditions, to Barrett's vision of the ideal role of the mental hospital within the community. The "Lecture Notes" were for a psychiatry course which Barrett taught at the Medical School, circa 1934.
  - Addresses circa 1920-1930s (Box 2)
  - Lecture Notes circa 1934, 3 folders (Box 2)
    (3 of 4 folders)
  - Lecture Notes circa 1934 (Box 3)
    (4 of 4 folders)
  - Reprints of Material by AMB 1905-1927, 3 folders (Box 3)
- Photographs
  Photographs [2 folders; c. 19th century- c.1930] contains Barrett's collection of photographs of prominent psychiatrists, and group pictures of State Psychiatric Hospital staff, with identification of individual staff members, which date from 1912 and the early 1930s.
  - Early Photographs of Doctors (collection), ca. 19th-mid-20th century (Box 3)
  - State Psychopathic Hospital Staff 1912, circa 1930 (Box 3)
- Case Files
  (open to research)
  Case Files [.5 linear ft.; 1906-1934 and undated] contains records of cases which Barrett treated, and some criminal cases for which he acted as a consultant. Several of these files contain personally identifying information regarding patients or criminal defendants, and are subject to a 100-year patient/client confidentiality closure.
  - Boyadjian, J.B. 1909 (Box 3)
  - Delirium Associated with Endocarditis and Cerebral Arteriosclerosis undated (Box 3)
  - Heart Disease, Psychogenic Factors undated (Box 3)
  - Lewis, Isaac 1907-1910 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous Cases (Box 3)
  - Motor Aphasia undated (Box 3)
  - Psychobiogram undated (Box 3)
  - Schizo-Mania undated (Box 3)
  - Tactile Agnosia undated (Box 3)
  - Tumor at Base of Brain undated (Box 3)
- Case Files
  (Closed to research for 100 years from the date of creation)
  - Dementia Praecox 1925, undated (Box 4)
    Closed to research for 100 years from the date of creation [ 2025 ]
  - LaCroix, James 1922-1932, 3 folders (Box 4)
    Closed to research for 100 years from the date of creation [ 2032 ]
  - Leopold and Loeb Casebooks 1924, 2 folders (Box 4)
    Closed to research for 100 years from the date of creation [ 2024 ]
  - McCormick, Stanley 1932-1934 (Box 4)
    Closed to research for 100 years from the date of creation [ 2034 ]